Guide to the American Jewish Society for Service Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
American Jewish Society for Service records
1948-2000
MS 1495
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
39.84
(45 boxes)
The records comprehensively document the organizational and operational history of the American Jewish Society for Service and its summer camps through administrative correspondence; meeting summaries; site documentation, including proposals, information packets, reports, and evaluations; publicity; and visual materials, including photographs, film, and videotapes.
American Jewish Society for Service
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the American Jewish Society for Service, 1989, 1994, 2001, 2002, 2005, and 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series and three additions: I. Administrative Records, 1948-1983 (inclusive), 1951-1983 (bulk). II. Chronological File, 1950-1984. III. Newsletters and Commemorative Books, 1960-2000. IV. Audiovisual Materials, 1951-1992 (inclusive), 1951-1984 (bulk).
Biographical / Historical
Henry Kohn, who earned his B.A. degree from Yale College in 1939 and his J.D. degree from Yale Law School in 1942, founded the American Jewish Society for Service (AJSS) in 1950. Since then, the organization has provided assistance every summer to various disadvantaged small towns, urban centers, and Native American reservations throughout the United States. The AJSS has also stressed to American teenagers the social and personal value of volunteer service through intensive manual labor. Advertisements soliciting high school applicants have appeared in major newspapers and public service bulletins throughout the United States each year. While most students are drawn from the Jewish American high school community, religion or ethnicity is not a requirement. Camper activities have included building, repairing, weatherizing, and renovating homes, shelters, churches, parks, and community centers, as well as clearing land, demolishing unneeded structures, digging ditches, and installing pipes and cables. To promote contact with their host communities and to foster the spirit of camaraderie, the AJSS also has provided the campers with numerous field trips, guest speaker presentations, and general recreational activities associated with camp life. Many Jewish campers also have used this time to explore the tenets of their faith through formal and informal discussions.
The first AJSS project took place in Indianapolis, Indiana, in July and August of 1951 when college students also qualified as applicants. Campers joined with Flanner House Homes, Inc., to help build single-unit dwellings for African American war veterans living in an impoverished section of the city. Religious life centered each Friday evening on the Kiddush and Sabbath observance, though religious affiliations within and outside of Judaism varied among the participants. Each work camp since then has been typically configured with a director, the director's spouse, one male and one female counselor, and, as of 1953 when college students were no longer asked to apply, ten to twenty male and female high school juniors and seniors at least sixteen years of age. The AJSS has provided food and housing at the summer project site for a modest fee, and project directors have arranged the recreational, educational, and religious activities. At the end of every project, the campers have compiled reports featuring their own poems and essays reflecting on the summer. Many also have written letters afterward, at the request of the AJSS, evaluating their experiences. By the mid-1960s and into the 1970s, as many as four AJSS projects were taking place at once, depending on the summer.
The AJSS celebrated its forty-fifth anniversary in 1995 and the completion of 106 projects in forty-two states.
American Jewish Society for Service Project Sites
1951 Indianapolis, Indiana
1952 Winchester and Southern New Hampshire
1953 Northfield, Massachusetts; Hawthorne, New York
1954 Morgantown, West Virginia; Fallsington, Pennsylvania
1955 Monteagle, Tennessee
1956 Winsted, Connecticut
1957 Yellow Springs, Ohio
1958 Fagleysville, Pennsylvania
1959 Frogmore, South Carolina
1960 Buckhorn, Kentucky
1961 Palatine, Illinois; Pierre, South Dakota
1962 Indianapolis, Indiana; Palatine, Illinois; Kiryat Haim, Israel
1963 Pine Ridge, South Dakota; Cherokee, North Carolina
1964 Macy, Nebraska; Cloquet, Minnesota; Rosebud, South Dakota
1965 Albuquerque, New Mexico; Palatine, Illinois; Bluffton, Ohio
1966 East Troy, Wisconsin; Babb, Montana; Bono, Ohio; Neapolis, Ohio
1967 Lackawana, New York; Lilbourn, Missouri; Crownpoint, New Mexico
1968 Northern Cheyenne, Montana; Clinton, Kentucky; Fort Duchesne, Utah
1969 Crow Agency, Montana; Ripley, Tennessee; Steamboat Canyon, Arizona
1970 Alamo, Texas; Fulton, Kentucky; Seaford, Delaware
1971 Mora, New Mexico; Abbeville, Louisiana; Madisonville, Kentucky; Woodburn, Oregon
1972 Tahlequah, Oklahoma; Abbeville, Louisiana; Waterloo, Iowa; Lewes, Delaware
1973 Richmond, Virginia; Crookston, Minnesota; Westmore, Vermont; Sisseton, South Dakota
1974 Opelika, Alabama; Orland, Maine; Tacoma, Washington
1975 Spokane, Washington; Greenville, North Carolina; Clinton, Iowa
1976 Rochester, New York; Grand Rapids, Michigan; Charlottesville, Virginia
1977 San Miguel, New Mexico; Springfield, Massachusetts; Madison, Wisconsin
1978 Hattiesburg, Mississippi; Des Moines, Iowa; Lincoln, Nebraska
1979 Wake Forest, North Carolina; Alice, Texas
1980 Goldsboro, North Carolina; Jeanerette, Louisiana
1981 Eustis, Florida; Hinckley, Maine
1982 Lewiston, North Carolina; Cannelton, Indiana
1983 McAllen, Texas; Des Moines, Iowa
1984 Jackson, Mississippi; Dahlonega, Georgia
1985 Amarillo, Texas; Fort Thompson, South Dakota
1986 Cincinnati, Ohio; Marty, South Dakota
1987 Cumberland, Maryland; St. Louis, Missouri
1988 Denton, Maryland; Laredo, Texas
1989 Chattanooga, Tennessee; Florence, South Carolina
1990 Wilmington, Delaware; Detroit, Michigan
1991 Chicago, Illinois; Everett, Washington; Topeka, Kansas
1992 Fabens, Texas; Four Corners, Louisiana
1993 Selma, Alabama; Fabens, Texas; Eugene, Oregon
1994 Eugene, Oregon; Phoenix, Arizona; Grand Forks, North Dakota
1995 Caribou, Maine; Tulsa, Oklahoma; Tucson, Arizona
1996 Tulsa, Oklahoma; Virginia City, Nevada; Twin Falls, Idaho
1997 McAllen, Texas; Salt Lake City, Utah
1998 Tulsa, Oklahoma; Kansas City, Kansas; Riverton/Casper, Wyoming
1999 Albany, Georgia; Escanaba, Michigan; Marquette, Michigan
2000 Santa Ana, California; Helena, Montana; Riverton, Wyoming
2001 Escanaba, Michigan; Las Vegas, Nevada; Rocky Ford, Colorado
2002 Marquette, Michigan; Taos, New Mexico; Tulsa, Oklahoma
2003 Hood River, Oregon; Rapid City, South Dakota
2004 Anchorage, Alaska; Sante Fe, New Mexico; Hood River, Oregon
2005 Grand Rapids, Michigan; Roseburg, Oregon; Vancouver, British Columbia
2006 Roseburg, Oregon; New Iberia, Louisiana
2008 San Juan, Texas; Little Rock, Arkansas
Scope and Contents
The records comprehensively document the organizational and operational history of the American Jewish Society for Service and its summer camps through administrative correspondence; meeting summaries; site documentation, including proposals, information packets, reports, and evaluations; publicity; and visual materials, including photographs, film, and videotapes.
One strength of the records is documentation of the organization's formation, growth, daily operations, and social service activities throughout the United States, from 1951-1984. The records also shed light on the impact AJSS work camps have had on certain impoverished segments of American society. Administrative files of general and project site records, photographs, and feature newspaper articles provide background information on the disadvantaged towns, city neighborhoods, and Native American reservations in which the AJSS has set up projects. The records also document the accomplishments of the AJSS at each site. Project summaries and reports reveal the ways in which impoverished communities have reacted and adjusted when AJSS volunteers have taken up temporary residence to perform manual labor, as well as to provide day care supervision and language tutoring. Summary project reports and AJSS promotional materials, including the annual newsletters and anniversary commemorative books, comprehensively illustrate the evolution of AJSS philosophy on Jewish-based social services in America, and how administrative experience and changing social conditions have refined that philosophy. Finally, evaluations from camp directors and counselors, letters by campers written to the AJSS, reports by campers, and photographs provide insight into the impressions, reactions, and changes in perspective teenagers have when, as AJSS volunteers, they meet and form working relationships among themselves, with adult leaders, and with residents of disadvantaged communities.
National service -- United States; Student volunteers in social service -- United States; Voluntarism -- United States; Young volunteers in social service -- United States; American Jewish Society for Service
- Administrative records, 1948-1983; Series I; 7.25
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents the philosophical foundation, administrative operations, and summer projects of the American Jewish Society for Service (AJSS). The general files under each chronological heading include a variety of materials explaining the ongoing goals and objectives of the AJSS. The various records emphasize how each summer project has related to the fulfillment of the AJSS's mission, and how that mission has evolved since 1951. The general files were used mostly by AJSS administrators as information resources for major reports, newsletters, press releases, and other promotional publications. The records include correspondence, meeting notes, project proposals, promotional articles and pamphlets, materials from other work camp organizations, and various forms of AJSS project documentation similar to what is found in the project files. Series V, Oversize materials, includes similar promotional materials in full page newspaper format.
  The AJSS project files, organized by location of the project each year, document specific summer work camps. The files provide comprehensive background information on the needs and socioeconomic conditions of each location. They include camp information outlines and site descriptions, general camper guidelines, correspondence between camp directors and AJSS headquarters, lists of campers, and articles from local or regional publications. The project files also include letters and reports written by campers--some with poems, essays, and creative prose--describing the impact of their work camp experiences; project site director and counselor reports used for evaluating summer camp organization, effectiveness, and efficiency; and letters and certificates of gratitude from host sites. If project files for a specific service camp do not appear in the inventory, the researcher should consult the general files for that year. There is no substantive information in either the general or project files on how AJSS decided on work camp locations.
  - 1951
    - General, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Stark, Irwin, correspondence file (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Stark was a work camp organizer.
    - Project file, Indianapolis, Indiana (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1952
    - General (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jewish organizations, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Project file, Winchester and southern New Hampshire (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1953
    - General (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - General (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - International Voluntary Work Camps, Coordination Committee (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Project files, Northfield, MA, and Winchester, NH, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - 1954
    - General, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Project files, Fallsington, PA, and Morgantown, WV (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - 1955
    - General (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - International Voluntary work camps, Co-ordination Committee (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Project file, Monteagle, Tennessee (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1956
    - General (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes evaluations by campers.
    - Project file: Winsted, Connecticut (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1957
    - General: Includes evaluations by campers, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - Incoming correspondence on potential 1957 project sites (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - 1958
    - General, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - 1959
    - General, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
    - International Voluntary Work Camps: Co-ordination committee (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - 1960
    - General, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - 1961
    - General, 1958-1962 (Box 4, Folder 32-35)
  - 1962
    - General, 1959-1963 (Box 4, Folder 36-38)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Israel Project (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - 1963
    - General, 1960-1965 (Box 5, Folder 41-45)
    - Clippings (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Financial reports (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - 1964
    - General, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 49-51)
    - General (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Clippings (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - 1965
    - General, 1963-1965 (Box 6, Folder 55-58)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - 1966
    - General (Box 6, Folder 60-61)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Babb, Montana (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - East Troy, Wisconsin (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Ohio sites (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Work Camps and other programs (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - 1967
    - General, 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 67-70)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Project files
      - Crownpoint, New Mexico (Box 7, Folder 72)
      - Lackawana, New York (Box 7, Folder 73)
      - Lilbourn, Missouri (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - 1968
    - General, 1963-1968 (Box 8, Folder 75-76)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Project files
      - Busby, Montana (Box 8, Folder 78)
      - Clinton, Kentucky (Box 8, Folder 79)
      - Fort Duchesne, Utah (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - 1969 1969
    - General, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 81-82)
    - Project files
      - Crow Agency, Montana (Box 8, Folder 83)
      - Ripley Tennessee (Box 8, Folder 84)
      - Steamboat Canyon, Arizona (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - 1970
    - General (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Project files
      - Alamo, Texas (Box 9, Folder 88)
      - Fulton, Kentucky (Box 9, Folder 89)
      - Seaford, Delaware (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - 1971
    - General (Box 9, Folder 91-92)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Project files
      - Abbeville, Louisiana (Box 9, Folder 94)
      - Madisonville, Kentucky (Box 9, Folder 95)
      - Mora, New Mexico (Box 9, Folder 96)
      - Mount Angel and Woodburn, Oregon (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - 1972
    - General (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Evaluations by Campers (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Project files
      - Abbeville, Louisiana (Box 10, Folder 100)
      - Lewes Delaware (Box 10, Folder 101)
      - Talequah, Oklahoma (Box 10, Folder 102)
      - Waterloo, Iowa (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - 1973
    - General, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Project files
      - Crookston, Minnesota (Box 10, Folder 105)
      - Richmond, Virginia (Box 10, Folder 106)
      - Sisseton, South Dakota (Box 11, Folder 107)
      - Westmore, Vermont (Box 11, Folder 108)
  - 1974
    - General (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - Project files
      - Opelika, Alabama (Box 11, Folder 110)
      - Orland, Maine (Box 11, Folder 111)
      - Tacoma, Washington (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Twenty-fifth anniversary planning, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - 1975
    - General (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - Project files
      - Clinton, Iowa (Box 11, Folder 116-117)
      - Greenville, North Carolina (Box 11, Folder 118)
      - Spokane, Washington (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - 1976
    - General (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 12, Folder 121)
    - Project files
      - Charlottesville, Virginia (Box 12, Folder 122-123)
      - Grand Rapids, Michigan (Box 12, Folder 124-125)
      - Rochester, New York (Box 12, Folder 126-127)
  - 1977
    - General (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - Project files
      - Madison, Wisconsin (Box 12, Folder 130)
      - San Miguel, New Mexico (Box 12, Folder 131)
      - Springfield, Massachusetts (Box 13, Folder 132)
  - 1978
    - General (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Project files
      - Des Moines, Iowa (Box 13, Folder 135)
      - Hattiesburg, Mississippi (Box 13, Folder 136)
      - Lincoln, Nebraska (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - 1979
    - General (Box 13, Folder 138-139)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Project files
      - Alice, Texas (Box 13, Folder 141)
      - Wake Forest, North Carolina (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - 1980
    - General (Box 14, Folder 143)
    - Evaluation by campers (Box 14, Folder 144)
    - Project files
      - Goldsboro, North Carolina (Box 14, Folder 145)
      - Jeanerette, Louisiana (Box 14, Folder 146)
  - 1981
    - General (Box 14, Folder 147)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 14, Folder 148)
    - Project files
      - Eustis, Florida (Box 14, Folder 149)
      - Hinckley, Maine (Box 14, Folder 150)
  - 1982
    - General (Box 14, Folder 151)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 14, Folder 152)
    - Project files
      - Cannelton, Indiana (Box 14, Folder 153-154)
      - Lewiston, North Carolina (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - 1983
    - General (Box 14, Folder 156)
    - Evaluations by campers (Box 14, Folder 157)
    - Project files
      - De Moines, Iowa (Box 14, Folder 158)
      - McAllen, Texas (Box 14, Folder 159)
  - 1984
    - General (Box 15, Folder 160)
    - Correspondence from campers (Box 15, Folder 161)
    - Project files
      - Dahlonega, Georgia (Box 15, Folder 162)
      - Jackson, Mississippi (Box 15, Folder 163)
  - General (Box 15, Folder 164-165)
  - Newspapers, large format, drafts and final distribution copies, and site-work blueprints, 1950-1984 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
    These newspapers advertise and promote the activities of the AJSS. The blueprints are related to specific project work sites.
- Chronological files, 1950-1984; Series II; 1.75
  The AJSS maintained a chronological mail file periodically throughout the 1950s and 1960s, and then continuously from 1970-1984. The file comprises both incoming and outgoing administrative correspondence with attachments. Included is correspondence with project camp directors, campers, officials from project sites, and donors. Camper address lists for the time period 1951-1970 are also included. Researchers should also consult correspondence in Series I, Administrative records.
  The series is arranged chronologically, and within each folder in reverse chronological order.
  - 1950-1953 (Box 16, Folder 1-15)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - 1962 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - 1964-1967 (Box 17, Folder 18-30)
  - 1969 (Box 17, Folder 31)
  - 1970-1980 (Box 18, Folder 32-42)
  - 1981 (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - 1981 (Box 19, Folder 44)
  - 1982-1984 (Box 19, Folder 45-49)
  - Undated (Box 19, Folder 50)
  - Camper address lists, 1951-1970 (Box 19, Folder 51)
- Newsletters and commemorative books, 1960-2000; Series III; 0.2
  This series consists of AJSS promotional material in the form of published newsletters and anniversary commemorative books. The AJSS began publishing newsletters in 1960 as a type of public report on the activities and accomplishments of each service camp. The newsletters include articles reporting on the projects and project locations, as well as pictures of the actual work and the names of all AJSS officers, directors, and campers involved. The anniversary books include articles of tribute describing many AJSS activities and accomplishments, as well as reproductions of all annual newsletters published in the time covered by the commemoration.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - Newsletters, 1960-1993 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Commemorative books
    - 25th anniversary, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - 35th anniversary, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - 45th anniversary, 1995 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - 50th anniversary, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 5)
- Audiovisual materials, 1951-1992; Series IV; 3
  This series comprises photographs, photographic negatives, film reels, and videotape. Black-and-white and color photographs include images of campers engaged in work or recreation, as well as work sites before, during, and after the project. Many of the photographs were used for promotional material for AJSS, including the annual newsletter.
  This series is arranged by material type. Photographs are arranged chronologically, and therein by project site.
  - Photographs
    - 1951-1953 (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
    - 1960-1963 (Box 21, Folder 5-8)
    - 1963 (Box 21, Folder 8A)
      Wood printing block of Elly Saltzman's 1963 group (Israel Project)
    - 1964 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - 1965 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - 1965 (Box 22, Folder 11-13)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 22, Folder 14-18)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 23, Folder 19-20)
    - 1971 (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 23, Folder 22-28)
    - 1977 (Box 23, Folder 29)
    - 1977 (Box 24, Folder 30)
    - 1978-1980 (Box 24, Folder 31-37)
    - 1981-1984 (Box 25, Folder 38-41)
    - Undated (Box 25, Folder 42-45)
  - Videotapes and film
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - KOAT TV, KOB-NBC, (Albuquerque, New Mexico), film, 1965; Commercially produced film (Box 26, Folder 46-47)
    - Unidentified film, Undated (Box 26, Folder 48)
    - Film negatives, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 49)
    - American Jewish Society for Service: Summer of Service, 1992; 1 (Box 27)
- Additional material, 1985-1991; Accession 2002-M-076
  Includes correspondence, camper applications and evaluations, mass mailings, reports, publicity and student publications. Types of files may vary within a designated year
  - Project files
    - 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1-33)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-32)
- Additional material, 1993-1994; Accession 2005-M-089
  - Project files
    - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
    - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
- Additional material, Circa 1950s-2008; Accession 2009-M-004
  Includes correspondence, applications, releases and evaluations, certificates, letters of appreciation and proclamations, and reports relating to AJSS project camps. It also includes Henry Kohn's 90th birthday celebration files. Types of files may vary within a designated year. No file for 1972.
  - Project files
    - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)